<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>languages on Karn Wong</title>
    <link>https://www.karnwong.me/tags/languages/</link>
    <description>Recent content in languages on Karn Wong</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2020 17:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.karnwong.me/tags/languages/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>ความน่าปวดหัวของการถอดอักษรไทยเป็นตัวโรมัน</title>
      <link>https://www.karnwong.me/posts/2020/01/khwaamnaapwdhawkh-ngkaarth-d-aksraithyepntaworman/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2020 17:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.karnwong.me/posts/2020/01/khwaamnaapwdhawkh-ngkaarth-d-aksraithyepntaworman/</guid>
      <description>*ตัวโรมัน = a b c d e f g &amp;hellip;
วันดีคืนดีชาวต่างชาติอยากมาเมืองไทย แต่จะมาเพราะอะไรนี่ก็ไม่ขอยุ่ง ไม่ได้สู่รู้เบอร์นั้น อนุมานว่ามาจากแถบยุโรป อเมริกาอะไรเทือกนี้ก็น่าจะเครื่องลงที่สุวรรณภูมิ ปัญหาที่จะเจออย่างแรกเลยก็คือ ชื่อป้ายชื่ออะไรไม่ได้ออกเสียงเหมือนที่ตัวโรมันเขียนไว้ เรื่องของเรื่องคือป้ายชื่อในไทยจะใช้ระบบ Royal Thai General System of Transcription ของ ราชบัณฑิตยสถาน แล้วปัญหาหลักๆ เลยก็คือมันไม่ได้สื่อว่าจริงๆ แล้วคำมันควรออกเสียงยังไง เช่น:
Thai Romanization Romanization System Pronunciation Source เทเวศ The-wet RTGS Tae-wet Pali-Sanskrit สุวรรณภูมิ Suvarnabhumi Devanagari transliteration Su-wan*-na-poom *&amp;lsquo;a&amp;rsquo; as in father Pali-Sanskrit ดินแดง Din-daeng RTGS Din-daeng Thai ศรีราชา Sri Racha Mixed:Sri - Devanagari transliterationRacha - RTGS See-ra-cha Pali-Sanskrit จะเห็นได้ว่าคำที่ต้นทางมาจากภาษาเดียวกันยังใช้คนละระบบในการถอดอักษรซะงั้น ที่เหนือกว่านั้นคือคำที่มาจาก บาลี-สันสกฤต นี่ก็ดันใช้ทั้งสองระบบถอดเสียงดื้อๆ โดยที่ไม่แคร์ว่าต่างชาติจะงงเบอร์ไหน</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Loanwords are okay</title>
      <link>https://www.karnwong.me/posts/2019/11/loanwords-are-okay/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Nov 2019 17:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.karnwong.me/posts/2019/11/loanwords-are-okay/</guid>
      <description>Does it matter if you language has a lot of loanwords? To be considered a loan, it has to be of foreign origin, and speakers from the borrowing end can understand and use in various contexts. It&amp;rsquo;s perfectly okay for the meaning to shift on the borrowing end, as semantic shift happens naturally. It does not make the word &amp;ldquo;unpure&amp;rdquo; or anything, it&amp;rsquo;s just how things happen. The borrowing language may have different point of view or context, so not all properties from the source can be carried over.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Indic name mistransliteration in Thai version of Harry Potter</title>
      <link>https://www.karnwong.me/posts/2018/10/indic-name-mistransliteration-in-thai-version-of-harry-potter/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Oct 2018 17:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.karnwong.me/posts/2018/10/indic-name-mistransliteration-in-thai-version-of-harry-potter/</guid>
      <description>I read Harry Potter as a kid, and I couldn&amp;rsquo;t shake the feeling that one character&amp;rsquo;s name is a bit off. I couldn&amp;rsquo;t quite pinpoint exactly why. Turns out, my hunch was right – the Thai translator used the wrong transliteration.
In Thai, &amp;ldquo;Parvati Patil&amp;rdquo; is &amp;ldquo;ปาราวตี พาติล.&amp;rdquo; This doesn&amp;rsquo;t even match the English transliteration (from Indic), as seen by a completely messed up second syllable on the first name. Because Thai language has a lot of influences from Indic, we also have our own system of transliterating Indic to Thai.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Definition of &#39;a Word&#39;</title>
      <link>https://www.karnwong.me/posts/2018/07/definition-of-a-word/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Jul 2018 17:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.karnwong.me/posts/2018/07/definition-of-a-word/</guid>
      <description>You often hear people say &amp;ldquo;you need to know x words in y language to be able to understand basic conversations.&amp;rdquo;. This is a bit misleading, since the definition of &amp;ldquo;word&amp;rdquo; is varied. For example, in Chinese (yes, I know, Chinese as a language doesn&amp;rsquo;t exist, but I digress) one character (one block) is one word. So this is easy. Then you have Japanese, where the same kanji (Hanzi, Chinese characters) can be pronounced differently, each with different meaning.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How angur became องุ่น</title>
      <link>https://www.karnwong.me/posts/2017/11/how-angur-became-ngun/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Nov 2017 17:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.karnwong.me/posts/2017/11/how-angur-became-ngun/</guid>
      <description>More often than not, Thai loanwords are of Indic, Khmer, English or Chinese origin. Although loans from other languages do exist. For instance, องุ่น (grape). This word is of Persian origin (read: Iran), which is انگور, literally angur. In Thai it&amp;rsquo;s angun. Notice that it&amp;rsquo;s n at the end instead of the original r. The reason is because in Thai r as end consonant doesn&amp;rsquo;t exist, instead substituted with n. For example, the Sanskrit loanword ahar is pronounced as aha[n] in Thai.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The confusing case of Thai romanization system</title>
      <link>https://www.karnwong.me/posts/2017/09/the-confusing-case-of-thai-romanization-system/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Sep 2017 17:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.karnwong.me/posts/2017/09/the-confusing-case-of-thai-romanization-system/</guid>
      <description>You decided to visit Thailand for whatever reason I don&amp;rsquo;t want to know. (It&amp;rsquo;s not my business.) Assuming you&amp;rsquo;re in from outside of Asia, you&amp;rsquo;ll land at Suvarnabhumi Airport. The problem? The locals don&amp;rsquo;t pronounce it that way. All the names and signs here are romanized using the Royal Thai General System of Transcription (RTGS). The big problem with this is that it is light years away of what Thais actually pronounce.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
